hi good morning again
all right welcome to class number two
for today
and my wife says my hair looks like
wings in the morning
okay sorry uh we're gonna
we're gonna start with a meditation and
before we start the meditation
uh i thought i want to show you a
picture okay
and i don't know i
like to find
great ideas in songkopa books
like you know but i also like to find
new desserts
because for me that's very important so
i was in japan
you know before the virus and
i went out to dinner with my friends
sophie chow and her husband
and uh we had and i was with stanley
nelson and we had this
japanese sherbet sorbet okay
and it's made from a special fruit it's
called yuzu i'm sorry if i don't
pronounce it correctly
it's called yuzu sorbei i know you
chinese people you have
youtu in china it's a different thing
that's a different fruit okay but the
name was taken from you
the japanese took the name from you but
it's a different fruit okay
so it's special and uh
if you're lucky and you go to a nice
japanese restaurant
especially in japan you can get this
youtu
sherbert you know and by the way i tried
to find it
in trader joe's and other important
places
they can't i couldn't find it uh
but it's unbelievably tasty okay
and this is the kind of thing where i
went to the
japanese restaurant with my friends in
tokyo and they took me out and
then came time for dessert my favorite
time
of the meal and
they say let's have youtube you know and
i'm like
no no no i i want uh green tea ice cream
i like green tea ice cream
they're like no no try youtube you'll
like it you know
and then i have this terrible
conflict in my heart you know because i
know i like
green tea ice cream but you know
you don't live in this world for almost
70 years and you didn't taste all the
desserts
come on you know so i'm like i don't
know i
how about i just have the you the green
tea ice cream there's like no
gesture don't be you know so stubborn
just try youtube you know
then i'm like all right let's try
yesterday you know and
it was unbelievable okay it was
totally unbelievable and nowadays i just
go around online trying to find somebody
who will bring you to arizona
uh maybe we can plant it at diamond
mountain i'm sure cat could
grow it uh why are we talking about that
geshe-la i'm saying
this whole retreat is trying to get you
to taste the yuzu okay this whole
retreat
is trying to get you to taste something
new
and you're gonna love it okay so
we're using 10 different ways
to get you to taste the youtube
ice cream sherbet okay we're trying
ten different ways just taste it no
no i'm too busy just taste it no i got
stuff to do you know
god just try it just taste it you're
gonna like it
and then you know i remember i took a
bite and i was like
okay forget the green tea ice cream
forever
now it doesn't matter anymore i need you
to
you know i need you to by the way don't
send me packages of you to ice cream
i have a small refrigerator what happens
after a talk like this like 20 people
send me
a crates of you to and then my wife gets
mad because i'm eating ice cream all day
okay so just taste it okay
just taste it taste it in 10 different
ways
get that taste 10 different ways so
we're going to do
you to meditation okay
here we go yiddish meditation get ready
for meditation
all right and we're going to go through
let's go through the images real fast
pal okay you ready
we're gonna go now you are serious
lamrim people you can do
10 different pictures in your mind
why we're trying to burn bodhichitta
into your mind we're trying to burn
a or etch a pathway in your mind
right neural connections
okay that's what meditation means we're
trying to etch the
silicon you know and and and make a
a neural pathway and we start with
dumb pictures from the internet and then
they get burned into your mind and then
later they become
uh reflexive they become reflex
and that's meditation okay so first
picture we're gonna do pow
is tennis player okay
just chase this bullet you know why god
you're gonna join this vip club planet
jumpers
planet jumper vip club wow okay so don't
forget
just taste it okay but this whole
retreat is to get you to taste it
the next retreat is how to get it
this retreat is just taste it just try
it
you're gonna like it okay why ten
reasons
what's the first one you join a whole
new team
you're gonna be this ultimate mvp
you know most viable player okay i think
that
apache i know you're argentinian so you
got to be a soccer fan
yeah so the super league failed
yesterday
right but anyway you could be on a
different super league right
all right number two picture number two
what's it mean graduation picture
yeah you get a whole new title what bv
[Laughter]
not bs okay
you know and they call you pachi the
bodhisattva okay yeah i'd like that
that tastes good to me i think i'll try
it okay
this is the whole point third picture bo
birds and the sun what's it mean
you outshined those other good people
yeah and by the way when i told you good
people i was using that word for
two kinds of people listeners
and half buddha okay got it okay
they're they're special they're
beautiful like those birds but they're
not like the sun
they don't fly like the sun okay next
picture pile
fourth picture coffee shop why
people can get good karma by serving
yeah
nice wouldn't that be fun to be so holy
that if someone gives you a coffee
they're gonna go to heaven for ten
thousand years or something
that'd be cool that tastes good
what did i say sujoo what's the ice
cream
yeah you do sorry that's how long i can
remember okay
it's hard to order it if you can't
remember the name okay
next picture
yeah bulldozers super efficient super
effective
stop picking up rocks one by one go get
a bulldozer
go get buddy if you want to make good
karma if you want to make enough good
comment to make a buddha buddy
rainbow buddy go get a bulldozer don't
don't go picking up rocks okay
what's the bulldozer
body chilling okay all right
okay next picture ketchup stain
it removes all of your bad stuff
yeah it burns it out yeah don't sit
there with the
soda water trying to clean the ketchup
stain just put
send the shirt to the laundry in the
middle of the sun
it won't last very long the stains won't
last very long okay
next picture shenzhen
garden like everything comes easy yeah
you can easily build all the stuff you
want
okay benefit number
seven of youtube ice cream
next picture eight tanks
yeah totally protected like you're in a
bubble you're in a diamond bubble
and all those problems just slide off
okay
all right number picture number nine
standing at the top of the mountain you
easily attain levels and paths nice
you easily complete the levels and paths
yeah you easily finish those
you go to path number five you go to
level number ten
all right last benefit
you become the biochar
for the whole world okay really you
become the super
fertile soil for the whole world the
you are you are the
cat used to get mad at me when i said
dirt gesture don't say dirt say soil
yeah you are the soil
that allows all good things to grow for
all people you
feed everyone quietly anonymously
invisibly under the rice under the weed
you're there all the time just making
people happy okay
cool does it taste good you two
okay again okay here we're going to do a
meditation
and again remember your goal
is to just remember these 10 pictures
so pick a story
pick an important event in your own life
i said like having your children or
going to high school or you know it's a
city where i grew up
i used to walk around i know all these
neighborhoods so i
the first pictures in this neighborhood
the second pictures in this neighborhood
then i know if i'm missing a picture
because i can't get to from this
neighborhood to this neighborhood
without going through this neighborhood
and i can't remember the picture
for this neighborhood okay so here we go
all right i'm gonna cheat i'm gonna have
the pictures in front of me
okay here we go sit up straight
relax your forehead
small smile
long exhales
deerga in the opposite long exhale
exhale ten times until your tummy
tightens
okay let's go through the 10 ways that
bodhichitta is delicious first picture
is what you guys
tennis player joining a new team
bodhisattva
burn it into your mind we'll take 10
breaths on each picture
burn the feeling into your mind
there's only a few people in this world
who can jump from planet to planet
connect with everybody
next picture what is it you guys
graduation i'm gonna get a new name
better than geshe michael buddy stopper
michael
and it will fit me
next picture
birds and the sun
there are beautiful people in this world
and they're they are beautiful but
to jump planets to help billions of
people that's a different level
completely
next picture
um coffee shop right
wouldn't it be nice to be such a
powerful karmic object
that if people just smile at you they
they would be happy for 10 years or
something
next picture
diamond mountain machine yeah
it's so powerful for collecting good
karma so
easy it's just a kind of thinking you
can do it
in your car
next picture ketchup thing
yay uh
send your bad karmas to the middle of
the sun
burn them up instantly
a bad karma cannot stay in your mind if
you are
thinking about loving countless people
they can't stay in the same
mind this town ain't big enough for two
of us
next big turn shenzhen
beautiful beautiful buildings parks
anything you want any project you want
to do
anything you want to accomplish just
work on your body children first
picture number eight tank
sitting in a safe in a tank
in the middle of the sun summer war
i protected in a diamond bubble
i can i can actually see other people
having
serious problems but they just never
seem to reach me
i have compassion for them but i
i i don't get those kinds of problems
next picture
top of the mountain i can reach the end
of the
body software level so i can reach the
end of all the flight paths
final picture
yeah a vast valley
of crops and i am the soil i am the rich
soil
everyone feeds from me
okay slowly open your eyes take a
stretch
pal's gonna show us to you too
yeah that's the whole story of this
retreat right is
come on just try it just taste it
then you after that you're like yeah
okay
next next time i go to a japanese
restaurant that's what i'm ordering you
know forget everything else
okay now i got really hungry i don't
know
all right let's go back to the text we
still have some time
[Music]
don't forget to connect those pictures
to some something in your life okay
that's something that happened in your
life okay your own life
and that'll be easier okay
uh let's see here
okay uh so we agreed that we were going
to cover half
okay what's a half buddha we finished
the tatwa buddha right
we established that all three
practitioners
know suchness they understand suchness
they saw emptiness directly
and it's the same emptiness okay
uh so what so why we call them half
buddhas
yeah what's the meaning of half
they have a head start of about a
hundred
kalpas from those listeners okay they
started earlier
and they have a lot okay
they don't have the following which is
why they are not
samyak sambuda total total perfect
buddha okay
they don't have they are short
what sunam and
[Music]
and really two collections they're short
on both collections
actually okay uh they don't have both
together
they are not uh they don't have
karuna compassion
they don't have compassion and so kappa
uh adds some words there
they don't have compassion for semchen
all the time they don't have compassion
for every living being every moment of
the day
okay that's that's what makes them
half buddhas okay and they don't have
tom j kemba they are not mister
no at all okay they don't see all
objects in the universe at the same time
past present and future okay and
therefore
they are ha
and half means sange men
says they just don't measure up
to full buddhists they're just not quite
there
okay there's a expression in english
close but no cigar okay they okay forget
the
sorry translators forget that one okay
all right and we have a medium picture
here pals got a medium picture here
yeah they're just medium okay i guess
red
is full buddha green is listener
and they got you know they've been
practicing
a few you know a bunch of million years
more
than the listeners but they're still not
in the red they're not total buddhas yet
okay all right
let's go on to the next section
[Music]
now somebody comes katy right tim what's
that
yeah some guy comes up i don't know he's
like
i i always see this guy with glasses
yeah but what about
what about okay
when you say buddhas have improved
in their collection of wisdom
over the hap buddhists what it means is
and if you live in a monastery
you know this is from arya sanghas
okay jewels jewels
of realization or something okay uh
you you've already memorized this when
you're 15 years old or something
eight years old
and it means uh
they specialize in the perception
of the emptiness of objects
as opposed to subjects they specialize
in the emptiness of objects
as opposed to subjects and there's a big
debate
is it easier to see the emptiness of a
pen
or is it easier to see the emptiness of
alex
which is easier there's it yeah pens are
generally easier
outside that's why when we teach dci
we don't get gail say up on the stage
and say think about her emptiness
you know we use a pen because in general
outside physical objects are easier to
talk about
uh when you're talking about emptiness
so
arya sangha in a in maitreya he's
he's being the what do you call the
person who takes the notes for the
for the businessman
the stenographer yeah the secretary he's
the secretary taking
notes for a sangha uh i'm sorry for my
trail
so really it's maitreya talking and
maitreya said
it's important to understand that it's
easier to think about the emptiness of
pens
but is that emptiness really different
from the emptiness of a person we would
say no
but some lower schools lower
middleweight
they started to say oh maitreya taught
different levels of emptiness you know
he was talking about half emptiness
and then full emptiness depends
emptiness is
half emptiness because it's easier to
see and
cats cutting them venerable cuttings
emptiness
is harder to see okay so there's a half
and a full emptiness and therefore the
half buddhas are
buddha which means uh they say have
emptiness okay
got it he's misquoting
is he a bad guy no half of the
middleweight school supports that
okay then jedson kappa says his very
funny
answer he says duh who wrote it
duh who wrote it what's it mean
who who's he quoting who's this guy
quoting
asanga no it's not a song is the
secretary
who my trainer you think my dread
believes in half emptiness are you nuts
you know don't don't misquote my traya
okay he gets upset at the guy all right
we don't call half buddhist
half buddhist because they see
half emptiness because they see the easy
emptinesses
and they can't see the harder
emptinesses because there's no such
thing
is it easier to see the emptiness of a
pen
than the emptiness of a person yeah but
are they qualitatively different is
there a difference
between the no mouse in cudding's
kitchen
and the no mouse in jordan's kitchen is
there different
no i mean it's a different kitchen but
the no mouse is the same i got it you
don't talk about half no mouse because
you have a half no mouse in your kitchen
you got
mouse poop in your kitchen all right try
to understand
it's important okay all right
why are we talking about all this guys a
lot we're trying to figure out
this idea of somebody's
giving birth to somebody else buddhists
are giving birth
to listeners and half buddhists
but where did the who's giving birth to
the buddhas
okay all right next picture here
pao you ready yeah
i don't know this i keep using this kind
of picture
how much emptiness
do you see if you're not a bodhisattva
when you see emptiness and you're not a
bodhisattva
how much do you see 100 yeah 100
zero 100.0
okay all right all right cool that's all
i don't know i probably could have found
a better picture i was probably tired
okay
uh
then uh some copper says by the way
chandigarh to himself master chandi
kirti himself
when he talked about this idea he
he said half
buddha doesn't really mean
50 full buddha that's not what the half
means
the half means 50 better than a listener
got it okay don't think he's deficient
he's better he went farther
a guy hunted campus father all right
he's just
don't think half means he's short of
buddhahood
think of half as he's halfway
beyond where the listeners are to full
enlightenment okay
cool
[Music]
don't think that there's some kind of
difference
in the practice even of listeners
from half buddhists they've just been at
it longer okay
they just went further they've so kappa
uses the word
expanded think of ha
as expanded they have expanded their
practice halfway to buddha to full
brotherhood all right
all right you got a picture here
yeah okay i forget why oh expanding okay
the
idea is expanding the road up higher
the road is halfway to complete
buddhahood
okay all right it took me a while to
find that one
uh danny talks okay
we have time do i have time yay
there's something we should finish today
okay because at the end of the class
we're going to say
yes
that's how the kids sound in the monster
it drives you crazy
to me you say do you know what
that means no that's why you go through
the gesture course okay
so he says we talk about the collection
of merit and wisdom and geshe-la taught
us a couple days ago
that when we talk about the karma
of a buddha we don't like to call it
karma
we don't call the seeds of a buddha
karma because karma is dirty
because even good karma is
dirty because it it wears out
okay the word karma is an insult
even when you're doing nice stuff
because it wears out
your body gets old your wonderful body
gets old right
your wonderful body was made by good
karma but it wasn't that good was it
because things keep falling apart as you
get that you will learn this joy
as you get older you know one thing
falls apart you go to the doctor you fix
it at great expense
and the next day something else falls
apart
i'll tell you a depressing story i was
listening to the radio
and a psychiatrist a famous psychiatrist
did a wonderful study of why
uh older people are committing suicide
more nowadays
there's more older people committing
suicide now
and uh partly it's because they don't
want to be a burden on their family
you know like it's compassionate they
they don't want to burden their family
you know but then the
the psychiatrist got a call to go
speak at a conference and at the
conference
she's giving the talk and she got a call
on her cell phone from the hospital
that her mother tried to commit suicide
okay
the psychiatrist's mother who's studying
suicide among the elderly
just tried to commit suicide but she
failed
and then you know she stopped the
conference she rushed home she talked to
her mom
and she said mom you know i'm the
world's expert on preventing
elderly suicide if you commit suicide
you know it does to my career
[Laughter]
you know what are you thinking you know
and the mom's like
it sucks you know just old age just
sucks you know
i couldn't take it anymore and she said
are you afraid i would spend a lot of
money taking care of you
no i'm just tired of it you know every
time you fix one thing
another thing falls apart she said the
problem is
it all falls apart at the same time like
it's not that you get sick and then six
months later you get better and then
something else
she says you get sick and something
falls apart and then the next day
something else falls apart the next day
something else
it all falls apart the speed
what do you call the acceleration of
falling apart goes
zoom and then everything falls apart
your eye's not working your legs not
working your ears aren't working
your nose not working you know anyway
why am i talking about that
that's dirty good karma okay that's
dirty good karma
so we have a tradition that we don't
call
the karma that has made a buddhist body
and a buddhist mind we don't call it
karma anymore we call it
the two collections and so jedson kappa
says
didn't you guys ever wonder that
collection word
maybe there's a deeper meaning and it's
beautiful like oh i'm sorry
tim said i'm going talking too fast it's
coffee and breakfast is looking at me
um okay
didn't you guys wonder
why we chose a word like karma
and we changed it to two collections i
mean is it kind of
weird right and so kappa says you're
right
it's weird and when you say the two
collections
it has a deeper meaning and and it'll
take me two minutes okay
it has a deeper meaning two collections
has a deeper meaning and and he says
well what is it
then he says let's do double dun cell
this is a famous commentary to my train
uh when we talk about
collecting the karma to create a
buddhist body
it means embracing it
in a perfect way
perfect embrace a perfect embrace
is the meaning of collection some bhara
say some butter
there's famous mantra somebody butter
butter mahapurusa
so the sanskrit
is sambana that nowadays
if you ask a sanskrit person
what's butter he'll say to carry
to carry something and we had it already
burden means that
bertha means that what's a spanish for a
wife
oh the sanskrit is berta which means
the thing you think masbae has to carry
okay
i'm sorry it's a bad one the sanskrit
word for
why is is berta something you have to
carry around
meaning you have to support them uh
and that's the ancient meaning of bara
sambara
means heavy load or something like that
and so kappa says
don't forget there's a more ancient
meaning of butter
and it's to hold or to embrace okay so
when we say the two collections
which is the two sambaras it means
the two perfect embrace he calls it the
perfect embrace okay
so he says don't when you
finish your class and you say surname
she told may i complete the two
collections he says
don't think of it like a bank account
don't think that if you put enough money
in the bank you become a buddha don't i
don't want you to think of collection
like that
that's not what collection means
collection
means your wisdom is deeper
and your good karmas are deeper your sun
and yeshi your merit
and your wisdom was perfected
to a point of perfect embrace
and you became that wisdom and you
became that
good good deeds you became wisdom
and you became good deeds and that's
what it means
to collect them got it beautiful
all right let's do that mandala who
wants to
tim uh final
final prayer
let's do both yeah
me
[Music]
yay